that you have a huge cost reduction and avoiding disasters. That's also very important. We
saw that computing started with doing batch jumps and we ended with social robots and what you
can learn from that is that instead of just being an appendix to the machine, the machine should tend
to the user's needs and that has made our work quite some more difficult because now we have to
make machines that understand the user in a certain way. Now all the visionaries and the
scruffy first prototypes that we have seen that's nothing to laugh at because these are the people
what we call the trailblazers who pioneer the technology for us and they take home messages,
know your use and context first before you start coding.
So let's continue with the history of HCI.
Here you see an example of scientists, technologists who envision in 1954 what a home
computer would be like. We are looking at the Rand Corporation and as you can see,
if your father was to buy this computer for you, you better clear out your bedroom because it's
huge, it even looks like a ship in a certain way. What do these people say of Rand?
Well, they have created this model to illustrate what a home computer could look like in the year
2004 but they readily admit that the needed technology will not be economically feasible to
the average home. Well they're right about that if you are building that kind of huge installations
that we see in the picture. They also say that the computer will require not yet invented technology
to actually work. That's also true but 50 years from now, we are talking 1954, scientific progress
is expected to solve these problems and they were right about that. We were able to make things smaller
with the teletype interface that's like the television screen that you see
and the FORTRAN language, the computer will be easy to use. Now that's kind of funny because we
now know that you cannot give users just a programming language, they will not know what to do with it
but FORTRAN, I always say in class, take notice. That's one of those very old heritage languages
and it's important because most of our financial transactions systems are still running on that
so even if you do your AliPay app by the end of the day what the bank has to do is run FORTRAN
language and the problem with software is that it can decay, it can go bad but there's nobody
hardly anybody who can still program and restore and maintain such old heritage languages
so it would be smart actually if you want to have some job security to start learning these old
languages and help Hong Kong Island maintain its systems. A close-up of the stretch, you see that we
are downsizing quite a bit, not the RAND Corporation personal computer because this is
already a kind of a supercomputer for the time 1960s and that's because it has so many transistors
inside. Quick overview, this is one of the circuit boards, it has 169 000 transistors,
one of the funny things is that the temperature is regulated in an oil bath to keep the performance
stable but it actually accepts the dedicated program languages but also something more general
like FORTRAN. Some important developments happened between the 1960s and the 1980s. In the mid 60s
it was still so that computers were too expensive for one single person and that's why they invented
time-sharing systems that gave the illusion of being on one's own computer but you were actually
all on one and the same mainframe with special workstations, terminals attached to it but it
dramatically increased the accessibility of computers, more people joining in and that led
to immediate need for human computer interaction because now you were dealing with interactive
systems and languages and not just batch jumps feeding commands to a machine and there was a
community that became a hole through communicating through the computers.
One of those things is that ergonomics became important such as the ergonomics of the console,
you get job control languages, the transistors are helping to make things smaller and by that it
becomes more accessible for people to work with not just financially but also ergonomically.
The interactive experience from the 60s to the 70s becomes an issue, you get interactive terminals,
command shells, speech, synthesis and then we have in 1965 the first PC ever, it is the
programa 101 by Olivetti and that's an Italian company, originally making typewriters and this
model particularly looks a little bit like a calculator that a shop owner would have on the
counter making up the bill for you so these older IDs are still visible in the newer developments
such as this first PC ever and computers are getting cheaper because of all of this, something
happens that is design rules that are made that are set up about personal computing,
it's not that anything goes anymore, people get the kind of routine of how to deal with that,
there are rules for dialogues, also in our assignments we will practice with those kind of
rules and video text services started to become apparent, you see one of those on the right hand
side the Minitel which is a video text system from France, now with all those rules happening
there are now suddenly in the beginning end of the 60s these computing conferences it starts to
become a science where they discuss document processing, hypermedia, input output devices,
the mouse, the one-handed quarter keyboard, high resolution displays, they start talking about
shared work so that's using context around the machine, how to share files, personal annotations,
electronic messaging, audio video conferencing already 1968, now we are on zoom and on
collaborate ultra and we find that all pretty normal, all IDs of an internet start to occur
and user testing last but not least and user training so like driving a car you should know
how to handle the machine apart from conferences HCI becomes a science with scientific journals
and two of these that you see in the lower left of the slide international journal of human
computer studies and ACM transactions on computer human interaction they are still Q1 highly ranked
journals and fully established and matured
also during the 1960s there are people who think beyond the current state of the art and are
envisioning how computing will be in so many years time so Joseph Licklider is one of those
visionaries and he tells us that the hope is that in not too many years human brains and
computing machines will be coupled together very tightly and that the resulting partnership will
think as no human brain has ever thought and process data in a way not approached by the
information handling machines we know today and that he calls man computer symbiosis we would now
say human computer symbiosis a famous paper by Joseph Licklider
and in his wake many others start to think about that we have a book on human machine symbiosis
from 1996 and then 2004 2005 Ray Kurzweil he's now owned by google is writing about the singularity
which would be near what does he mean by that if you do a you should know the word singularity
because it is the idea that at one point computing intelligence would be so great that it emulates
human intelligence and then go beyond so it will be better one day that than humans can think and do
now that's a quite big claim of course and there are some aspects to it that may be right and I
will also tell you a little later about aspects to it that are not there yet
but it is true that we have things like what Joseph Licklider said brain computer interfaces
particularly people who are impaired in my example here they they are paralyzed
they can control robotic arms using their brains so a signal is picked up played through
the computer to the external arm the robotic arm and then the robotic arm will actually execute
what the person is thinking so they are able to reach and to grasp objects that way in a 3d
space using the robotic arm and they control it directly with their brain activity and you can
even think about neuro gaming at the moment there are brain computer interfaces that they try to
integrate with gaming so for instance where you look is where camera position will go or an action
that you can execute while thinking of it and yeah we are in a way close to become cyborgs
because we all have a granddaddy with a pacemaker or a grandmother with a cochlear implant for hearing
or people who have artificial lenses imagine a person who has it all a pacemaker cochlear implant
artificial lens an exoskeleton blades to walk on chips under the skin to check in at the bar
metal joints knee and hips also has to go into the hospital for kidney dialysis or maybe when
things are really going bad be kept alive in an intensive care unit that's very close to being a
human computer symbiont now i was referring to the international journal of human computer studies
i recently had a publication there which also includes the singularity and it actually says
the singularity is far from near one of the problems being what do you mean about human
intelligence or artificial intelligence well in the experiments that we did the we couldn't find a
trace of it that people would experience something like that in state-of-the-art robotics if you
want to have a look go ahead as you can see international journal of human computer studies
is a life and kicking but back to joseph licklider who in a way uh was trailblazing was the forefront
of all of this in that famous paper man computer symbiosis he writes down a couple of goals short
term midterm and long term goals and it's quite remarkable how many of these things turned out
to be an agenda for developing technology that we are using today because we do have that time
sharing of computers among many users we don't do the time sharing anymore but we have sharing of
computers and information among many users no no no problem with that electronic input output for
display and communication of symbolic and pictorial information well everybody has symbolic and
pictorial icons on their desktop or interactive real-time systems for information processing
and programming yeah we do have that large-scale information storage and retrieval we have that
too we have data farms we have big data retrieval analysis all of it intermediate goals the facilitation
of human cooperation in the design and programming of large systems that we do many software houses
have people abroad working together online do we have speeds recognition yes we do do we have
hand printed character recognition yes we do do we have light pen editing well look at the upper
right hand corner that's already 69 the hypertext editing system it's already there and also nowadays
we have styluses on our tablets then the long-term visions natural language understanding well up to
a certain extent we do have natural language processing we can do syntax and we can do semantics
but what's still hard is pragmatics we don't know the role of the use of language yet
can you say the sentence when you are in an informal setting in the bar can you say that
same sentence also at the formal setting when you shake hands with the president you you will be
different in the way you are talking and that's something we as scientists still don't really
understand yet and therefore it's hard to teach to a computer so that's well one third of that
point is still under development um speech recognition yeah we have of arbitrary computer
users yeah still we can do that maybe not always perfect but it's there and heuristic programming
yeah with all the fourth generation languages and for instance with graphical computing where you
have two icons and you put an arrow in between that's heuristic programming you don't really
have to know the language anymore now let me introduce to you ivan sutherland most people
would consider him the least cool guy in the schoolyard because he looks like a bookkeeper
with his big glasses um i think he's the most cool guy in the schoolyard and let me tell you why
in 63 he develops the sketch pad and that's a drawing tool and what he does is he structures
in a hierarchy particularly defined pictures and sub-pictures well we know that now right we
are using icons aren't we and he does something that we now call object oriented programming
i think that's pretty cool that's something we do now a master picture with instances
those have constraints you can specify details which the system maintains through changes that's
also new icons well we know i can small pictures that represent more complex items you can copy
those both the pictures with the constraints and you have different input techniques with the
efficient use of a light pan and all people with tablets and a stylus are indebted to ivan
he actually develops the first graphical user interface the gooey
so yeah apple makes soft user interaction the future i think ivan sutherland made soft
user interaction the future so yeah steve jobs um ivan never heard of
ivan sutherland he also goes into hardware in the following way he he helps to develop
low-cost graphical terminals creates input devices such as data tablets which we still
have data tablets and display processors capable of real-time manipulation of images
and maybe even more impressive for us today he is the developer of 3d computer graphics
and head mountain displays gamers pay tribute because those vr treadmills that we have nowadays
they are directly indebted to the work of ivan sutherland you see that head mountain display
it's almost like a helmet it needs to be kept up by that huge construction because otherwise
just too heavy on your head but it's the first vr that we know and therefore ivan sutherland
is your big granddaddy gamers most of you didn't even go into a vr treadmill but yeah they are there
and they are the latest thing and you can show off to your other schoolmates but it's that old
daddy that actually was making that possible how was it possible that an old daddy like that made
that possible well because of the following this is his philosophy it seems to me that the most
important thing that adults need to do with young people is not squash their curiosity
but to help them exercise their curiosity and learn how to use it remember edison telling you
make a lot of mistakes now remember ivan telling you be curious don't be put down don't let the rules
restrain you in what you want to do because if rules are telling you what to do you won't do
anything new you can be you cannot be curious you can only follow the template
and he is another hero not following templates ellen k i'm sure nobody ever heard of him we are
talking uh 1969 it's all about personal computing what he does is he developed a dyna book that's
how he calls it and it's the vision of a notebook now even some of the current computers laptops are
called notebooks what does he say imagine having your own self-contained knowledge manipulator
well we all carry our self-contained knowledge manipulator we call it pc we call it tablet and
we call it mobile phone in a portable package the size and shape of an ordinary notebook well
that's exactly what we have suppose it had enough power to out raise your senses of sight and hearing
well it does gpu far faster than me enough capacity to store for later retrieval thousands of page
equivalents of reference materials well we all have that we have papers and pdfs and articles
all on our machines poems letters yeah letters we do have letters emails recipes yeah people keep
recipes on their knowledge manipulators records drawings yeah and not just artistic drawings
but also technical drawings animations many people watch animations musical scores people listen
to music on their machine and all of that came from cardboard prototyping nothing fancy no big
prototypes on digital machines just trying out low level building it after the vision that you have
he had tiles he had the stylus and then people can try out the good thing is
less costly redesign if things don't work out the way you want a very good way to start developing
new systems and we will do this too in our assignments you will do low level prototyping
and just learn how it is to not digitally digitally understand the requirements of the user
so yeah the apple macbook air is fully indebted to that idea of the
dyna book that ellen k developed so also for ellen k steve jobs never heard of
during that same period a little later in the 70s there's also something that comes
from the more the the hackers kind of subculture there are people now such as ted nelson who see
that all computing power is assembled by for instance ibm and only made available to other
companies and they resist that what they want is that computing becomes operational accessible for
all people that that's his computer liberation dream machine he wants deep computer literacy
among all members of the community of society it's a kind of counterculture that we still
see today like i said particularly the ethical hackers are a good example of the follow-up
of what he wanted and against the centralization of computers such as ibm
nevertheless the business type of computing just goes on no matter what this is the xerox park 1973
and xerox may be a boring company because it's all about photocopy machines but they're not that
boring because they are really going into personal computing with a graphical user interface and one
of their first machines is the alto computer a personal workstation with a local processor bitmap
displays and a mouse for that time very very modern they also have graphical interface with text
drawing editing electronic mail like we now have email windows menus you see that that's that's not
an invention by microsoft windows and menus and scroll bars mouse selection etc and the local
area network the ethernet using the shared resources particular thing peculiar is that the
disk screen display screen has a portrait orientation
all right let's do a quiz item now you should raise your hand if you know who it is have you
ever heard of ad mccrank he's a very famous man very important for computing but i'm afraid nobody
heard of him what about chuck fecker chuck fecker you don't know this is butler lampson do you know
who butler is but butler is very famous very important for particularly human computer interaction
who's bop sprout you don't know or dav borgs still don't know well he's an important technician
you know for the other things we do today on our computers uh steve jobs now all hands are raised
right but steve wasniac people are not so sure about yeah what steve wasniac was the technologist
let's say but then how come among all of these technologies that the only one who is the least
technological is the most famous and then usually my students say quite righteously
because he's great at marketing and so he was because look at this the xerox park that's the
latest of xerox you will see that the ones who were actually making that computer are
the computer after the alto is the result of a joint effort by ad mccrank which he didn't know
chuck fecker but the lampson bop sprout and dav borgs and they were attempting to make a device
that was small enough to fit in an office comfortably yet powerful enough to support a reliable high
quality operating system and graphics display and this gooey featured in windows and icons
and only a few years later so you know they didn't invent it they just went after it
steve jobs and steve wasniac borrowed some of these ids and started apple computing
and they borrowed from ellen k and from ivan sutherland and etc etc
1980s the xerox star again personal computer but now commercialized it's a personal computer for
business professionals you see just like ibm and against the computer liberation movement
the first comprehensive graphical user interface using many ids developed earlier with the xerox
park it now has a familiar conceptual model with a simulated desktop it promotes recognizing and
pointing and not so much remembering and typing it has property sheets to specify the appearance of
objects also the whole idea of what you see is what you get we think it's very modern but it's
already there in the 80s with a small set of generic commands that could be used throughout
the system with a high degree of consistency not too difficult a modulus interaction
however with limited amount of used customization and this is one of the reasons why it didn't
really fly this xerox star 8010
but it is the first system based upon usability engineering it is an inspired design with
extensive here we go again paper prototyping not technological prototyping and the analysis of
use what do people do with it a lot of usability testing going on with potential users and an
iterative refinement of the interface exactly like i told you before this is the way to go
however and that's why it's so hard and that's why you need to analyze use not only use but
also context it was a commercial failure because the cost uh 15 000 us would still be a quite a
price for that kind of computer and unfortunately the competition ibm just announced a less
expensive machine it was limited in its functionality it had for instance no spreadsheets
and that was not too smart a closed architecture so you could not use any other software on it
than the xerox allowed you it was perceived as slow but actually really fast in other words
be aware that you may overclock your gpu but that people don't necessarily feel it that way
this is why you do user experience research it may on the clock be faster or slower but it's not
necessarily that people will perceive it that way and the xerox star was too strongly adhering to
direct manipulation so you could not if you wanted pop up the c prompt and type in something
of a command the 1980s the user becomes more and more important and is approached more naturally
there are systemic principles to deal with users and how users would deal with their computers
there's a human protocol now windows and graphical interfaces are more or less becoming standard
PCs gain in power and they can store data or mainframes they have graphics and already speech
processing one of the commercial machines during that period coming out is the apple lisa and it's
based upon many ideas of the xerox star the predecessor of the macintosh that we now know
and it's somewhat cheaper ten thousand dollars still quite a price however still a commercial failure
so as you can see although it is building upon developments created by others already knowing
that you shouldn't overprice it's still a kind of fine tuning that apple has to do because before
they become a success and they become a success in 1984 the apple macintosh personally that's also
my first acquaintance with apple and why is it a success because many others invented what then is
old ideas but now they can improve them and do them real well and they also succeed not just because
of technology but here we go again with the context they have a very sharp pricing it's a relatively
cheap twenty five hundred dollars and it didn't have to do all the pioneering the trailblazing
being in the forefront because that's costly right they were just waiting for the time to be
ripe and they corrected the mistakes of their earlier lisa now they have mature ideas the market
is ready so if you want to upload your newest your latest game to google play be sure that people
actually wanted that they are ready to pay for it otherwise it will just sit there also smart
they had a developers toolkit by which you could use those third-party softwares that were non-apple
they had interface guidelines uh they wanted consistency between applications that's what
they still do and also very good they developed an infrastructure around the machine they developed
they were dominant in desktop publishing because they also could deliver a affordable laser printer
that was the latest hottest thing at that time with excellent graphics and still apple is the
preferred operating system machine to work on if you want to do graphics however in spite of all of
this they have a strange thing in their interfaces particularly in the older ones such as this apple
macintosh people if they want to store something they want to keep you put it on a disk in those
times it was called a floppy disk but then if you want to eject the floppy disk you have to trash it
now that's not very smart because trash and a bin are not related to something you want to keep
so from an association semantic point of view it's not really smart to have people throw things
away in order to get them out of your machine and also in the more modern versions that I
showed you on the right hand side you still need to pull the external drive to the trash can
but then luckily it changes it to another icon for ejection but it still has has that counter
intuitive feeling of trashing to eject from the 1980s on until now the user takes center stage
all of your applications have to deal with how users are going about we have integrated
multimodal systems you can handle the same app from your telephone as you can from your pc
there is something called ubiquitous computing word you should know all computing systems out
of your face you don't need to sit behind the screen type something in but it's in your house a
smart home the internet of things we interact with it without directly typing in or clicking something
some systems try to detect your emotions in order to adapt to it also in gaming you will find that
one of the ways to do that for instance you see on the right hand side is that they measure
physiological data for instance heat so a red forehead would indicate surprise or a cold
face would indicate fear but be very careful with that that a hot forehead may also be because i'm
stressed or i feel love and a cold face may also be because the heating is not on
so important lesson emotion expression doesn't mean that i feel the emotion i can also play being angry
all right lessons learned from the history of hchi in the old days computers would cost more than
people do today people cost far more than computers do and applications can now afford to trade off
processing power for human usability it doesn't have to be faster and even correct um because
humans don't even perceive that anymore new ideas often don't make it into products straight away
there is a long time of development before something becomes market ready the pioneer systems
they develop the innovative designs like ellen k for instance or ivan sutherland but often they
are commercially not viable yet see the xerox park settlers systems so they are after the
pioneers they settle down they incorporate very often all of these older ideas many years later
but then well researched they did a lot of hchi work with users iterations prototyping make designs
that now are evaluated as good better than before and so they are ready to market
so what is hchi today it's not just computing it's also computing but it's also hardcore computer
science it is also artificial intelligence you will need to deal with people who can engineer
you will encounter cognitive psychologists you will have to deal with people who know about
ergonomics or in other words human factors sociologists people who know about communication
anthropology linguistics industrial design you name it it's all there
an example from computer science very close to the hardware you may or may not know that the
united states have a problem with people who want who want to cross the border from mexico to texas
and the u.s department of homeland security they want driver's licenses with an rfid tag
that you can read from a distance to use for patrol of the u.s mexican border
however such a rfid tag may be reprogrammed with a virus here comes the virus and that was tried
out here we have the ethical hacker culture but one of my former colleagues in the v u
university of amsterdam melanie rebach and she invented the first rfid virus so by that she
showed that this kind of identification is a kind of dangerous but she also comes up with a solution
so computer science is the programming of the virus but now the engineering is that she comes
up with something different than just computing she comes up with a circuit board with two antenna
and onboard processors and that intercepts the signals from the rfid readers and like a software
firewall it now doesn't let those signals reach the rfid unless you want them to for example if
you're passing through customs so by that it's far harder to put viruses on that rfid and user is in
control or what about this artificial intelligence many of these self-driving cars have a problem
kill people because it decides not to swerve so not to go around it and the cars sensors saw the
woman but may have flagged the detection as a false positive what you learn from that is that
artificial intelligence has a direct effect on usability and particularly on the on the
other stakeholders in the car such as people on the road who are killed by that machine
and that's because the ai is not good enough you cannot just test in perfect circumstances
the ai cannot handle these exceptions why is that because exceptions are not in the training set
or they are getting very low weights so what it can do is handle all the known patterns what it
can hardly do is handle the unknown patterns and this is exactly what humans do better than any
computing system they do one trial learning that's one one aspect the other is even situations they
have never ever encountered before they can handle and that's really something different from what any
ai may do
yeah you will also encounter the Douglas Engelbart of this planet the engineers who was augmenting
human intellect with a conceptual framework well it wasn't that conceptual it was actually this
little mouse uh with a you know with a little box that was falling apart almost and two wheels
going left and right and up and down um that's the type of person you also need to do that
that's the type of person you also need to deal with because you need now to code
something completely different from a keyboard
and yeah nowadays we all find that normal the logitech revolution mouse but the revolution was
actually in what Douglas Engelbart did that that scruffy little wooden box
cognitive psychologist why is your computing directly related a one-to-one link to psychology
well this thing that you should program for remembering me or a module for for getting
passwords or for getting an account name the people who study memory and recognizing and
forgetting those are the psychologists so you are programming that because people have that kind of
psychological issues let's say memory overloads courses security issues because passwords are too
simple and now you have to make something that you know warns the people that the password is too
simple sometimes they are related to the user self they repeat the same password everywhere
you need to know all of these things to make something to uh accommodate that kind of behavior
or they forget passwords so your programming routines they make up for user error and that's
the direct link between requirements on the system the human side and what you will code what you
will program on the backhand ergonomics or in american english human factors that's more on
the physical input output side this kind of pens for instance to avoid repetitive strain injury
you also see these single-handed ergonomic keyboards there have been many experiments
with different layouts in keyboards and different forms of keyboard it never really flew but you
can see they tried to change the ergonomics so that the hands would be spared not strained too much
you can also think of the ergonomics of a vr system when you get like motion sickness or in this
case the gate recognition suit all of that is either limiting you or it gives you possibilities
you didn't have before that's ergonomics what about sociologists why why would you know about that
well think of social media and how people make posts or make their moments on we chat and that's
not just for diary purposes it's also to establish social groups to show your affiliation to show
that you're a particular type of person going to these exhibitions or that cool festival or that
you know this important provost of the university all of that is sociological behavior and you
want to know how social networks are functioning in order to have your new social media app make
any chance in communication there's something a special section called computer mediated
communication because these people found out that not every medium is fit for every purpose
why do we nowadays do face-to-face teaching again because for the task of teaching that seems to
be better than me emailing you with the same content you know same information but I just put
it on the email or that we would have a social media app and app around the questions and the
remarks and I do the teaching on this that's not really fit however there are also situations where
social media would be preferred over face-to-face or where you would write an email for instance you
may be very angry and you want your money back from the company but face-to-face you flare up too much
so by emailing you have time to think to rephrase and then you send and you don't say I am mad at
you but I'm highly surprised I've also seen particularly boys breaking up with their girlfriend
through an app I don't love you anymore sorry yeah what's that you know hiding behind the media
that's what people do because in a face-to-face confrontation then you need to explain and
the girl starts crying and you have an hour of talking and why yes and why no and who did what
and everybody blaming everybody else and it takes another hour and a third hour of crying
and that's really far harder than just saying I don't love you anymore sorry
anthropology what's that well that's actually the study of humans in a culture and that could be
international culture like people from China versus how do people in Japan deal with mobile
phones or people in Europe but it's also occupational culture so culture on the work
floor the the culture of Xerox will be different from IBM or different from Google and all of
that weighs in that's used in context on how people deal with your systems example the Nokia
that that was the iPhone of well let's say the early 2000s one of their new features was calling
line identification and in western countries that was really nice because now you could see that the
bird was calling you but in non-western cultures that didn't fly particularly not in India why
didn't it work in India well because in India you have this caste system very strong hierarchy and
it is a matter of respect that when your boss is calling you that you will recognize his voice
and then say hello boss so nice that you are calling me but now because of this identification
of the caller you can immediately see the name in the interface and you can say hey Sanjay are you
there so that was really like a misfit of the feature that somebody programmed and
that went to market and did well in western cultures but was really not good in India
this is anthropology the study of how people deal in different cultures with your interactive systems
he is an other example of anthropology culture and interactive systems now people with a
muslim background they know what the burqa is a burqa is a long cloth like you see here in blue
covering all including the face of a woman's body that's a requirement from the religion
women should not be visible for whatever reason however in the west they thought of well that's
something now we have somebody showing the burqa on the catwalk but we cannot see who's underneath
so they integrated some bluetooth technology into the burqa and then you could through your mobile
phone see who was under the burqa by which the very function of the burqa in orthodox
muslim culture is annihilated so that was kind of insulting for that kind of people with that religion
because it's exactly that you should not know who is underneath and not look at the woman with her
hair hanging down and you know the neck being visible
linguistics nowadays with large language models like gpt that's pretty obvious and we have siri
and alexa google assistant cortana that's all operated through the voice but something interesting
that linguists will tell you is why it is so that it's easier to go from text to speech
than it is from speech to text text is an abstraction from speech everybody speaks
differently it's not just that we have accents we also have our individual accents idiosyncrasies
they call that and the letter r spoken by one person differs a little bit spoken by somebody
else the third person the fourth person etc so it's far harder there's far more variability for a
computer to recognize an r but in text that r is the same for everybody so it's easy to
generate the sound from a text because it goes from very strict text to ever a more variability
whatever voice you use for it but the other way around is hard many different options
that should be pinned down to only one the r or the p or the t so this is why it's so that it's
harder to go from speech to text than from text to speech and knowing that information
that's why you need linguistics may help you define the next generation of speech to text
applications
and then industrial design pretty obvious i mean why would anyone buy a macintosh
they love the apple iphone because of its design just how it looks but also these kind of
keyboards that are resistant to water alcohol or you can roll them up put them in your back
all of this or they light up in the dark all of this will have an effect on what you can code and
what you cannot because a corded keyboard takes other technology than a wi-fi keyboard for instance
so yeah you will practice with understanding users through experiments
we will do task centered system design you will develop task examples and evaluate your
designs through a task centered walk through so you go together with the user through the
different stages of the system asking them how does it feel did you understand you will have
a webcam to see how they move how they do you will also for instance if you do use a technical
device you can do the click logs other user measurements and you will design with the user
that's user centered design and prototyping you will have methods for designing with the user
and most importantly the best is to use low and medium fidelity prototyping so like i said you
can have a paper mockup or a paper prototype and at best maybe put it into a powerpoint and people
can click through the slides you will learn more in the remainder of this course about the role of
evaluation in design how to do user tests and how to observe people using systems and detect
interface problems in designing interactive systems you should ask yourself what makes a
visual design work it's the placement of interface components on the screen that's for one and i've
seen websites where you have to scroll through five pages before you can click the okay so just
that okay button is not visible you have to look for it but it's also about representations and
metaphors what are metaphors well look in the lower left corner the home button there's no house
involved there's no home there some people would even say yeah but that that's the starting menu
yeah but menu also has nothing to do with food in this case those are metaphors like we have
metaphors for trashing the trash can the bin or maybe a magnifying glass to search but it's a
digital search you don't hold a magnifying glass so metaphors are you use an item from one category
in order to represent an item from another category so home comes from architecture
but you use it to represent an aspect of a digital interface that's metaphor and you will see if you
go through your own interfaces how many metaphors we stack one upon the other there is also principles
of design we even have one well law of design which is fits law if you look into the little
algorithm you don't need to know the algorithm by heart if we are gonna use that on the exam i
will give you the algorithm show you what everything means and then you can eventually calculate with
it basically comes down to this an interface item can be large or small smaller is harder than larger
it can be close by to click it and it can be further away to click it
further away is harder than close by so if you have a mouse that should click the small button
or click the large button it's pretty simple to say what should be because you know that
large is simpler than small however if you only have the screen real estate of a phone
you can make things bigger but then you can only place two items on it so where's the optimum
what in these ambiguous cases that you have a smaller item far away or no a smaller item close by
or a larger item further away well then that's what you need then is what you what you should do
is calculate fits law so it can show you if i go with my mouse to the large item or from the
large item back to the small item how correct and how fast are we in doing that
and this is one metaphor for you the home button
all right all in all humans are good at sensing of low level stimuli so if you are designing
for humans you can have let them do that they are far better at pattern recognition than any AI
system is they can do inductive reasoning so they need a few signals in order to understand
already what the course will be they can handle multiple strategies at the same time they are
very adaptive and they can create computers are best at counting measuring so let them do that
they can accurately store and recall data very fast consistent in their responses
they can do data processing usually better than humans do calculate and do a lot of repetitive
actions without getting bored however currently we also make computers that are moving up the rank
so they are doing pattern recognition there is something called artificial creativity that we
now have and up to a certain extent it can do what humans do but like i said there's a limit
to it so be careful not to overshoot your goal by thinking your AI can do things that humans
don't need to do anymore that's not true they should collaborate
so in this course here's the summary for you we have taught and we are teaching
why HCI is crucial in system design and how to make sure that users become an integral part of
your thinking it's not just coding language it's not just shall I do python or C sharp
human computer interaction is not only important to create nice user experience it's also to avoid
costly redesign to sell more products or services and we have seen shocking examples where bed design
caused human disaster with nuclear power plants or with airlines airplanes
now by definition HCI is concerned with design with implementation and with evaluation of interactive
computing systems for human use and it provides input language for the user output language for
the machine and a protocol for both to interact in the historical context that we saw the focus
is shifting away from humans servicing computers which in a way is simple for us programmers
because it's only the computer you need to deal with the humans will adapt to it
but nowadays we must make systems that can serve as humans so now the system must be
more adaptive and that's very hard to do therefore you should work with many disciplines that can
collaborate because you don't know everything that is to be known a computer system should fit
human use therefore go into computer science social science mathematics psychology physics
you name it all of that is needed for interaction design if you don't do a poor HCI design makes
even you as the toughest computer on earth look stupid
okay let's practice with an item on your exam something you may expect we have three
different types of questions one is knowledge so you just remember what fits law is about right
or you have an application that's applying something you learn to for instance the
example of the fat finger syndrome you remember with the stock market in japan
or you get a inside question now you have to relate two knowledge items to one another such in this
case how is fits law related to the fat finger syndrome then you get a number of answering
categories and usually one of them is total nonsense and the others are pretty okay but
there's only one really correct and most complete and you always go for the most correct and the
most complete answer answer one a stress worsens performance or b fits reckons with the width
ratio between pointer and interface widget or the logarithmic distribution for fat fingers
differs from for instance mouse pointers or a and b are both correct so now it's for you to think
you must know what fits law is you should know what the fat finger syndrome was about and then
relate the answers to that question so here we go it's a and b that are correct why do i say
well let's first look into fits law it was that the wider an interface which it is and the closer
it is to the pointer then the easier it is to hit it and particularly when the pointer is wide as
well the fat finger yeah so in the stock market that man made a big mistake he had big fingers
and he was pointing to a small thing in the interface hitting another button as well and now
he sells at the wrong price and the whole tokyo stock market suffers from it so in this case
it's easy to hit with a big finger something small it's about the pointer to target width ratio
not target width alone that's why it's b and yes it's also true that people make more errors
under stress what this teaches you is that you can formulate an algorithm that can be an ai
algorithm or a fits law algorithm but it only focuses on an aspect of the problematic in this case
the size of things in the interface and how quick and how correctly you can touch it but there are
always things in the context and in the use and in the situation that people are operating so fits
law also is under those constraints of in this case stress so fits law under stress works a tiny bit
different from fits law under a relaxed situation so be aware that algorithms are not the holy
truth they only separate one single aspect from a far larger problematic
importance of hei and why you should look into other things than just computing and programming
here the solution to the fat finger syndrome is solved not through making another interface
not through coding but through ergonomic design what do i mean i think you have a grandmother
somewhere who does needlework you know needle and thread but to stick the needle through the cloth
or the textile she uses a thimble she puts it on her finger and then pushes that needle through the
cloth now creative designers like in the school of design they will think of hey i have one item
in one category but it bears some similarity to an item in another category why not make the fingers
smaller instead of making the target widget wider so they use the concept of a thimble
adapted to operating an interface and now the whole fat finger syndrome is solved
through creative design this is why you want to cooperate with other disciplines because no computer
scientist would ever have thought of using a thimble in order to operate an interface